okay and we're away um welcome everybody
to the third episode of active inference
insights brought to you by the active
inference Institute I'm your host darus
pvy Wayne and today I am absolutely
thrilled to be able to speak to John BVI
John is an award-winning professor of
psychology cognitive science and
Buddhist philosophy at the University of
Toronto he is also the presenter of the
renowned YouTube series Awakening from
the meaning crisis as well as the newer
after Socrates his work focuses on 4E
cognitive science which holds that
cognition is embodied embedded enacted
and extended beyond the brain in
particular John explores relevance
realization our adaptive ability to zero
in on salian information in a world of
near infinite complexity last year he
Mark Miller and Brett Anderson wrote the
paper predictive processing and
relevance realization exploring
convergent solutions to the frame
problem which proposes that tradeoffs uh
trade-offs in Precision waiting a key
second order dynamic in predictive
processing hierarchies are at the heart
of our ability to be intelligently
ignorant and that alignment of predicted
processing and relevance realization is
exactly what we're going to be talking
about today John welcome to the show
thank you so much for joining us it's an
absolute treat thank you Darius uh a
great pleasure um I'm uh hoping that
Mark does make it on in December uh
that'll be great yeah absolutely but in
his absence because Mark was meant to be
here today but it's uh unfort he's not
unfortunately able to make it um perhaps
so this podcast is acting as a kind of
primer an introduction for our audience
to the critical themes in cognitive
science and psychology and biology as
well as maths and physics as they are
right now um so I think it would be a
worthwhile uh worthwhile place to start
if you could just unpick what relevance
realization is and then we'll come to
how it aligns with predictive
processing sure uh so relevance
realization is um sort of inverts the
way Common Sense Works common sense is
there's a lot that is obvious to us and
we know what it's obvious what we should
pay attention to we're sometimes
mistaken but it's obvious what we should
be remembering and what we should be
doing and that's all obvious and we just
run from that um our job as cognitive
scientists is to explain how the brain
generates that
obviousness that salience Landscapes
that makes the right things stand out as
relevant to us so that we can do what is
astonishing solve a wide variety of
problems and a wide variety of
domains um you're a general Problem
Solver which is just astonishing I mean
you can learn Albanian history you could
learn about swimming or rock climbing
you can take up the study of dinosaurs
in the Jurassic period like it's just
you know and it's just amazing and
astonishing and there's good empirical
evidence you have something like a
general intelligence there seems to be a
general capacity there's individual
variation and talent some people are
better at learning this domain than
other domains but there way back from
Spearman we know there's some sort of
General ability uh I'm going to propose
that the general ability are two
interlocking things the anticipation and
relevance realization what I mean by a
general ability is the these are kind of
meta problems these are the two big
problems you have to solve when you're
doing any other specific problem solving
and what makes relevance realization so
hard generating that obviousness so
mysterious actually that's what Scott
atran says he he says that what science
does is it makes what common sense to
take takes to be obvious mysterious
here's a table in front of me but
physics says well what is that really
and mysterious and it's made out of
quarks and all this sort of stuff it's
the same sort of thing here because when
you think about it um outside of common
sense you realize that there's just an
overwhelming amount of information
that's constantly as you said
dynamically changing in the environment
there's an overwhelming amount of
information in your long-term memory
that's constantly changing and being
readjusted during to to the
reconstructive nature of memory there is
an overwhelming number of combinations
of actions you can perform see sequences
of actions and yet you ignore that
overwhelming almost all of that
overwhelming information and zero in on
the relevant information so that you are
oriented right in the world finding
things obvious Salient standing out and
you're and and it's and it's not just a
single thing there's like a salience
landscape some things stand out more
than others some things are more
foreground background you have all this
happening so that you are capable of
solving so many problem problems in a
messy complex World in which there's
constant novelty because of an emergent
phenomena and trying to give this
ability to machines has been
overwhelmingly uh difficult and one of
the hard hard problems we're actually
bumping up right into it now as we've
finally taken up the AGI project the
project of trying to create artificial
general
intelligence excellent um it may be
worth digging a little bit deeper into
that Exposition um because people might
be thinking well don't we just have a
module for relevance or salience don't
we just kind of we're born and we know
oh um I should not fall off cliffs and I
should but actually what happened
yesterday might be quite irrelevant you
have a wonderful um explanation in your
sort of keynote paper explicating
relevance realization where you say that
leads to an infinite regress um perhaps
you could explain
that argument so the magic module not to
be confused with predictive processings
reported problem of the magic modulator
so let's keep those two distinct from
each other but the mag the magic module
is well I have a I have a relevance
realization thing in my head that just
does it and then that just and then I
can just say well how does it do it and
the mistake people can make is well
Evolution made it and that's right
Evolution tells me how it got here
that's not telling me how it functions
Evolution tells me how my eye got here
and how my ear got here and that's not
telling me how my eye and my ear
function I'm trying to take What's
called the design stance how could tell
me what I need to do to give that module
the ability to realize relevance you you
all you've done is said it has that
ability but it faces the problem of okay
now it has to know what to pay attention
to and so on and so forth now what you
might say is well Evolution totally
prepared us for it the the problem with
that is that doesn't work uh Evolution
can only pick up on things that are
longterm invariant and that make an
ongoing
continuous um difference to your
reproductive uh status right and that's
not how relevance Works relevance is
really fast and changing if I say left
big toe it suddenly becomes relevant to
you and it wasn't relevant a minute ago
and what's the darwinian difference
there um and there's nothing that's
intrinsically relevant well my own life
is intrinsically relevant is it you'll
sacrifice your life for your kids well
my life and my kids right under all
circumstances you know what if you know
saving your kid means that 10 million
people oh well and so on and we get into
all these philosophical arguments
because we realize no no there isn't any
hard fast thing that is always relevant
relevance is not something for which we
can generate a scientific theory it's
not stable it's not intrinsic to the
phenomena
and it there's nothing other than being
relevant there's nothing that all the
events or objects or feelings have in
common like what is it that what do they
all have that makes them other than
saying well they're you'll give me
synonyms they're important to me or they
help me solve my problems yes that's
exactly it but how but how exactly
perfect and it's it's so nice to see how
the um apparently disperate strands of
cognitive science so gibsonian
affordances fory cognitive science
predictive proing processing and act of
inference a line at this path which is
that everything is dynamical everything
is about this Mutual unfolding there is
no rified static um existence it's
what's relevant to you might not be
relevant to me and there are these
Dynamic relationships which govern that
um it's yeah so that's that's a that's a
great place to start I think let's now
go into uh the solution if there is such
such a solution and let's start with
opponent processing so this is a term
that you use
frequently and to a Layman audience it's
not clear exactly what it means so what
what is opponent processing and how does
it help shed light on this complex
problem sure um and maybe along the way
I can point out how relevance
realization really gives some specific
tee to claims of embodiment from for
eoan because I I'd like the point you
made and maybe we don't have to do it
right now but I'd like to come back to
it how relevance realization is kind of
a glue that glues together predictive
processing and for e cogi in powerful
way and makes them all including itself
mutually stronger from that integration
uh but yeah the opponent processing so
let's just note something at many
different levels of analysis in your
biology you will find opponent
processing at work work I'll take one
that's very easy to explain and people
have a ready experience of it uh so we
are all constantly mostly unconsciously
although it's affected by conscious
factors we're constantly recalibrating
and adjusting I dare I say it we're even
evolving our level of metabolic arousal
I don't mean just sexual arousal don't
be freyed here I mean arousal how much
how much how how sort of activated are
you how sort of energized are you um and
the problem is there isn't isn't some
State you homeostatic State you're
looking for with that because if there's
a tiger in the room I need to go to
maximal right arousal uh uh and if I'm
going to sleep I need to go to minimal
arousal and I can't just be sort of
Canadian and keep sort of average
arousal at all times because then I
don't fall asleep and I get killed by
tigers and so it constantly has to be
like we're talking about has to
constantly readjusting so what what has
evolved in your biology is your you're
autonomic meaning self-governing it's a
self-organizing system like you said
it's a dynamical entity your autonomic
nervous system and what it does is it
couples together two
subsystems that are have opposite biases
from each other your so your sympathetic
system is biased to I I'll speak
anthropomorphically just because it
speeds things up your sympathetic system
is biased to seeing as much of it can of
the world as threat or opportunity and
arousing you as much as it can and your
parasympathetic system is biased the
opposite way it's biased to seeing as
much of the world as secure safe A place
where you can rest and recover and then
these subsystems are not independent
from each other they're locked together
and they're they are ALS they're
continually trying to shut each other
off and they're constantly competing
that way but they're cooperatively
competing it's not adversarial they're
cooperatively competing and what happens
is the constant tradeoff between those
those proc between those processes
constantly right in very Dynamic manner
constantly recalibrates your level of
arousal to the world and that's opponent
processing and what you find is you got
that you know there's other there's
opponent processing between your focal
vision and your peripheral vision
there's opponent processing plausibly
between your left and right
hemispheres the number of these things
like uh uh is huge and I say at many
different levels of analysis um and so
um I think opponent processing is a clue
uh to how relevance realization is
actually undertaken by your embodied uh
cognition wonderful and immediately to
anyone interested in Act of inference or
um its manifestation in continuous State
spaces as predictive processing it what
we'll be screaming out is this notion of
an attractor set for our homeostatic
equilibrium which Carl has spoken about
at length obviously and and as has many
other researchers but this idea that
what this we are we suffer um but we
also uh embody in a kind of positive way
this itinerancy we we never we're never
stuck in a single um mode we we are owed
with the capacity to go beyond our
homeostasis and return back to it but
we're always in a sense being drawn
without ever residing ever without ever
having stopped at that homeostatic set
point um so let's now fold in active
inference to the picture what does it
provide relevance
realization um and the formulation of
relevance realization that couldn't be
done purely with for cognitive
science so I mean I'm going to talk
about it in terms of predictive
processing because that's the one that's
the formulation of it that lines up most
cleanly uh with the theoretical
integration uh as you said there's
there's clear derivation relations
between active infant and predictive
processing and also between them and the
basian uh math but the basian math if we
were to actually strictly apply it would
be computationally intractable so we're
doing some approximation function so I'm
just going to take it that everybody
sort of knows that I'm playing fair with
this right I'm not I'm not trying to be
Dodge you here um and so um relevance
realization
is grounded in uh the idea of problem
solving and problem solving actually
assumes a fundamental thing which again
is so obvious to us which is the state
you're in and the state you want to be
in are not the same state that's the
defining feature of a problem if I'm in
a state I want to be in I want to be
sitting in this chair I am I don't have
a problem um right and now what that
means is you're all you're you're
immediately into something very
interesting the organism is trying to
actually predict a possible state in the
world and prepare itself alter so it's
an agent it doesn't just behave it
Alters Its Behavior to alter the con the
states in the world right and so it is
trying to I would say predictively
prepare for the world it's trying to
predict the world but prepare itself for
that world but also prepare the world so
it's more likely to come out in the
prediction that it's seeks right and so
I I put those two together um and I I
talk about
anticipation um and so you're whenever
you're problem solving you're
anticipating a goal meeting that
prediction and preparation now for EOG
site doesn't directly talk about that as
as clear as it needs to it talks about
coupling and it talks about affordances
and I think there's a deep connection
between opponent processing optimal
gripping and affordances and maybe we
can that at some point uh but typically
one of the things where uh 40 kogai has
some challenges is in more distal
relations uh to the environment because
it tends to rely primarily on coupling
and you know this is a long-standing
critique that one of my colleagues Brian
kwell Smith at the University of Toronto
because that is where all knowledge is
Flowing from um right uh has made he
said you know uh you can be predictively
coupled to things that you're in direct
causal contact with but you know uh um
uh sorry dynamically coupled not
predictively coupled my my apologies uh
but you how do you do things that are
much more distal and for me that that is
key and here's why
darus I think in I think when we
evaluate even
intuitively um so I'm not using that as
an authority I'm just showing how
readily this works for us um when we
evaluate an organism for its
intelligence we tend to to it in two
interlocking ways is we do it in terms
of I think how how well does it zero in
unrelevant information how well does it
pay attention to what it needs we look
at an animal we go wow that's really
good you notice how it's noting subtle
differences but we also evaluate the
intelligence of an organism and Michael
Levan talks about this with this
cognitive light cone idea is How Deeply
into the world they can anticipate and I
don't mean just spatial temporally I
also mean it Mally possibility like when
I talk to my cat and I say you know you
know where's your toy the cat looks at
me and I go oh well right I say to my
puppy where's your ball and she goes
into the other room looks for the ball
finds it under the coach and brings it
all the way back to me I go wow you're
really smart right and so we get this
because we we know how just Moment by
moment that adaptive ability is built on
what how dist can we pursue goals we
tend to evaluate people wow you pursued
a long-term goal and you brought it
about so that's what's missing and I
think that's what what's really afforded
now I want to make one more point and
then I'll I'll shut up so you can you
can ask me another question which is
these two issues anticipating more
deeply and remember I don't just mean
spatial temporally I mean Mally and
relevance realization are deeply
interconnected the more you anticipate
the more the problem of relevance
realization goes up exponentially and so
these two things right they I I would
argue because they're interlocking they
have to be solved together and I think
that's why we use both of them as
evaluations of the intelligence of an
organism okay I'd like to backtrack to
that second
argument after this after what I say
here it um yeah it it strikes me that
what predictive processing can give
perhaps where fory cognitive science
doesn't but I'm happy to be schooled on
this um and I know verel and Auto pesis
in some sense pre- shadowed um and
prefigured what I'm about to say is that
it kind of gives a ground to our action
and to our perception which is that we
have to have a model of the world and a
model of ourselves which is not only
descriptively viable but also
normatively viable yes in so far as it's
all like it's very important for me to
be able to predict the world but as you
said we aren't just at the behest of the
world's Dynamics we can change the world
according to our preferences
exactly and I think what predictive
processing gives us is although although
to be fair I think Carl might say that
this is a bit of an overshoot is a is a
Telos is a fundamental attractor set to
which our perception and action is is
governed so I think that's kind of the
way that I see the the added benefit of
this convergence between um predictive
processing and um relevance realization
what I was also going to say there is
that it's fantastic that you're
mentioning this kind of deep temporal
modeling because for my eyes that's
really where a lot of the the work is
being done right now which is that
selfhood Consciousness even perhaps
space itself is Downstream on the fact
that we can Downstream on the degree to
which we can model the slower Dynamics
and the faster Dynamics in a generative
hierarchy so that's I think that's I I'm
in complete agree that I think that's an
extension of the argument I made uh yeah
and so what I wanted to pick up there is
you said if I heard correctly that the
more the the deeper your temporal model
the more you can model slower
fluctuations in the environment the more
critical relevance realization becomes
the higher the stakes in some sense yes
yes very much I'm interested in
unpicking that argument because for my
eyes there there are plenty of things
out there that don't have deep temporal
models
so um I don't a virus for example would
just be reacting to very uh Co brain
features of the environment but for them
relevance realization at least to my
eyes appears as critical as it would for
a human it it is it is and and so I
think it's how how can I put it I think
it's always a demanding problem I'm so
I'm not I'm not denying that even uh the
uh the parium has to uh do salience land
cap aping it has to I'm going to use a
word very neutrally here I'm not conting
anything about Consciousness but it has
to recognize this molecule as food and
that molecule as poison and swim
reliably towards the one and away from
the other I'm not I so I think the
problem is always there as I was trying
to indicate as soon as you have problems
as soon as your goal states are distinct
and I think the space opens up very
quickly exponentially I just meant that
it exponentially gets worse right this
this is is why you see uh across species
hyperbolic discounting temporal
discounting because that's a that's a
huge relevance realization machine it's
about salience discounting right and the
point of that is is because as you open
into the future the number of
possibilities goes up exponentially and
so you need to have this attenuation
function so you don't get overwhelmed by
the possibilities as you extend your
cognition into the future that's why we
have hyperbolic discounting and we pay a
huge price for it it makes us procras
makes us difficult to give to pursue our
long-term goals so there's even a
trade-off relationship in there but I
won't get into it but that's an example
there's a good reason why we must have
something like temporal discounting
across species that's what Angley showed
is because the relevance realization
issue just it gets even worse it starts
out bad and gets even worse right
wonderful and yeah I mean a lot of your
work we we we'll come to affordances now
because a lot of your work is centered
on the notion of affordances yeah
affordances are the possibilities for
Action afforded actually circular
possibilities for Action granted by the
environment I mean afforded was a verb
and then Gibson made now um how much has
the predictive processing framework
supplemented your understanding of
affordances and perhaps the way that
what we perceive in the world is not
necessarily a feature list of objects
but um they are fundamentally
affordances I see my glass of water as
gri
rather than being glass this Dimension
and I only ask that because as I said as
as conscious animate cognizers we are
blessed with the capacity to change the
world in accordance with our priors
which makes action really the
fundamental currency yeah for autop
paresis for self-organization so does it
has predictive processing ramped up the
uh importance that you give to gibsonian
affordances um I don't know if it ramps
up because I I always thought uh I I
literally learned this stuff from John
Kennedy uh when Gibson's greatest prot
so from very early on I was very much uh
impressed by this um and it it occurred
to me that relevance
realization um the realization of
relevance and I mean realization in both
senses actualizing a possibility and
becoming aware of it or at least
detecting it in some fashion um that it
it's a prototypical kind of affordance
the thing about affordances is they're
not found in the object or in the
organism the grip ability of the glass
is not in the glass can't be gripped by
paramuseum and it's not in my uh you
know in my hand my hand can't grasp
Africa or the sun right it's it's in a
fitted relation between them and that's
exactly what relevance is it's a fitted
relationship between so I always before
I I came into a a deep dialogue with
with predictive processing I already saw
a deep relationship between relevance
realization and affordances and I think
um part of my work has been to really
explore the Deep ontological
significance of that that you have a
category that sort of Falls outside this
was Gibson's intent too this is what 4
Eide is really talking about Falls
outside are our belief that we have a
complete exhaustive dichotomy between
the subjective and the objective between
the inner world and the outer world and
so there's this other important I call
it the transcor this betweenness this
connectedness you see in adaptivity you
see in relevance but you also see it
like you said now what do what do I
think the predictive processing did I I
I it's if you'll allow me I want to talk
this just I want to talk back and forth
symmetrical not just linear so I think
what the predictive processing does is
emphasize the need to try and explain
rather than
just I don't want to be cruel so I'm
being a little bit overs simplistic I'm
doing that just for Speed sure but
generally it's like yeah but how do the
affordances get actualized in the 4E
coln like there's a lot of affordances
all the time and what I'm interested is
when how do those affordances become
well Salient and obvious to me so they
become binding on my sensory motor
behavior and that was always something
of uh you know not that you know there's
Redfield and others who were doing some
work on it but to typically they start
to invoke predictive processing to try
and explain that mechanism of like okay
there's a there's a huge affordance
network but I'm not like how do I here
we go again how do I select and
actualize the ones that I'm actually
going to that actually go into my salian
landscaping and I think predictive
processing especially with the notion of
precision waiting does a good job of
that now what I think relevance
realization helps to do to predictive
processing a bunch of other but one
thing is predictive processing basically
there's subtlety to this and I know
there's lots of math but just to keep
going right that you know well what
attention is is the Precision waiting
it's this meta function and I think
that's a very good argument but there
but there's a conceptual analysis that's
been needed but it's like but what is
saliens and one of the arguments I can
make is well what the Precision waiting
is doing is relevance realization and
relevance realization uh when relevance
realization re does a higher order
finding relevant of an affordance that
has been generated by lower order
relevance realization that's when
something becomes Salient to us and so
we can actually give a conceptual
exclamation that goes with the
theoretical identity claim in predictive
processing the Precision waiting is
attention and what it gives you is
salance so they can they can unpack each
other I think what another thing that
happens
is relevance realization is deeply
connected to for Eide because relevance
is grounded I would argue in auto
pois um relevance relevance is always
relevant to an organism right and so
that means relevance realization isn't
called calculation it's how the organism
cares about some information rather than
all the other information because it is
constantly taking care of itself there
are literally and I mean this physically
things that matter to it and things that
it must import into itself important
things and some of that's also
information and so by that if you if you
can if if you can glue for EOG sign
predictive processing together I think
you can answer some of the questions
maybe even challenges that some people
in for E cogi are making a predictive
processing and saying well it's not
really connected to embodiment I think
no no if you show a deep theoretic in
theoretical integration of predictive
processing relevance realization and
then relevance realization and autois
then you've really strongly glued
predictive processing and for E cogi
together so that's some of the that's
some of the important theoretical work
that can be done yeah absolutely I I
would love to jump into um the critiques
that certain fory um cognitive research
uh cognition researchers have leveraged
at predicted processing but let's um
let's leave that for a second this is
exactly what I was talking about in
terms of Telos um which is that exactly
this this notion of care and and when I
spoke to ma alaras in an active
inference research
um last week we kind of actually ended
up concluding this is almost the
hiigaran sense of care that on our
existence can I can I just interrupt
there yeah right that hiigaran sense of
care was exactly what I was in invoking
and I right and I was deeply influenced
by dfus and the frame problem got this
from haiger right so the the connection
you just drew is very I I that yeah I I
explicitly argue for that excellent so
yeah I mean I personally think um that
the hiig hiigaran draus Merlo Ponty
lineage needs to be integrated more into
yes active inference and I'm speaking to
Dr Marilyn stendera who has done work on
hyar and auto paresa so that will be
really that would be really fun in the
upcoming weeks but this is exactly what
I was talking about in terms of Telos
which is that taking a stance on your
own existence can be computationally
modeled as having these kind of high
Precision priors yes so our homeostatic
set point will be different from snakes
and that actually gives a really solid
explication of why we act differently in
certain context than snakes um and so
that was my kind but then that said I
will have to make clear that
Carl is in himself although he has
spoken about existential imperative says
that there actually is no imperative all
that you're really saying is if a thing
like us is to persist over time this is
what it needs to do and it's just a it's
just cast as a minimization of free
energy so I think there's an interesting
question there that maybe you could have
a go out which is to what degree do you
see this as a genuine imperative um
versus just what things do to
self-organize over
time yeah and so I mean and and uh
Carl's no SLO so he's welcome I I I
sometimes don't like it when people who
you know are physicists or something
start commenting on philosophical uh
normative questions uh with an authority
they don't properly possess uh but I
know I mean Carl's a great theorist and
um and I know he's philosophically
educated um I have not yet to talk to
him but I hope I do get to do so we can
do
ahead so
um yeah I mean so I'm gonna argue later
if I get a chance that what relevance
realization doing is strongly
analogous uh obviously a very different
time scale uh to what evolution does
about constantly uh uh redesigning the
adapted fitted of the of organisms to
the environment and allowing organisms
to fit their environments to them
because as you keep emphasizing and I
keep agreeing with it's not passive it's
not right the organism is shaping the
environment as the environment is
shaping the organism Niche construction
and all that sort of thing um and I
think that's all right and I and then
there again that's a very clear
connection to for Coogi again but this
deeper question I do want to do it I
want to pause and I want to slow down
because it's it is a really important
question uh because it gets us beyond
what we might call scientific
explanations of how and into properly
but not useless philosophical reflection
of sort of why and why does this matter
to me because as you've mentioned I'm
deeply concerned with you know issues of
meaning in life this this this largely
metaphorical nebulous notion that humans
seek meaningful lives lives that are
worth living even given all of our
failures and our faults and our flaws
and our foolishness and our frustration
right and pretty clear empirical
evidence that it's not
reducible uh to just subjective
well-being or pleasure and pretty good
conceptual philosophical argument
because it's that's where it's relevant
that it's not reducible to just living a
moral existence you could live a very
moral existence in which you're sort of
experiencing the pleasure of food and
other things um and and and you you know
certain stability in your environment
but you can be very very lonely you
could be very lonely um so and what what
that loneliness points to I'm just
making an intuitive gesture that's not a
tight argument I have tight arguments
but the the gesture is people are
seeking a kind of connectedness and now
you see where I'm getting to relevance
realization and what we're talking about
this Niche construction the fitted the
belonging togetherness this mutually
shaping like this is this I argue that
that's exactly the connectedness human
beings are they're seeking the meaning
in life
now you can then ask the question and PE
and I'm going to play with two terms of
phrase here to play with that I think we
clearly seek meaning in
life uh and I think the evidence for
that is growing and it it converges with
the psychological work on meaning in
life and on what Karen Allen calls
belongingness if you don't feel that you
belong you're in trouble and you're in
trouble across all these measures
cognitive emotional social Financial
blah like you're in trouble
physiologically you're even in trouble
um that's why solitary confinement is
such a punishment right um
so is there a meaning of life to the
meaning in
life the meaning of life is is there
some sort of
cosmic Destiny Cosmic order to which we
are ultimate which we are ultimately
trying to
find and here's the thing I don't think
I have enough evidence for
that I think that there's lots of
evidence for meaning in life and if I'm
right that it's relevant realization and
if that's something very much like
Evolution right evolution is constantly
redesigning
adaptivity but there isn't a final thing
that evolution is aiming towards there
isn't a final form of life there isn't
some like what we're doing is like the
sculptor we're constantly refining and
then finally one day we will have the
final form of life and um I think this
is fundamentally flawed and I think this
matters philosophically I don't think
previous forms of life were in some in
in any kind of moral sense Superior to
us so I don't believe in any Nostalgia
some the previous things that people
found important and relevant and sacred
those were the true ones and we just
have to get back there nope and I don't
believe the Utopia we are working
towards the final ultimate thing that
we'll all agree for all time is the most
relevant most Salient I I don't believe
that how this works so I reject
nostalgias I reject Utopias the idea
that there's a TS can either mean
there's a TS to meaning in life which is
it's like Carl says it's necessary it's
constitutive necessary for living things
to have this but does that mean there's
any metaphysical necessity to their
being living things things that's a
different question now here's my weak
answer at that one sorry long question
but you asked like this is like almost
up there with like God question right
right I note that I'm in a very
difficult situation I can't see any
evidence for and I'm not attacking God
here as you know I'm very respectful and
even appreciative of of religious
Frameworks and religious lives but I
can't see any evidence for that however
if you were to ask me which is a better
Universe one with life in it and one
without life in it even if you couldn't
exist in either one I would say the one
with life in it there's some primordial
judgment going on there um that has some
kind of metaphysical import now it's
weak I I I admitted that ahead of time
and so I'm giving you a very I'm sorry
very long but wishy-washy answer I don't
really think I believe anything like the
meaning of life but I do think there's a
metaphysical import to being connected
to reality we find reality being
connected to reality inherently valuable
for its own sake and we find worlds in
which things can realize reality better
worlds than ones that don't have that in
it that's my answer no it's a wonderful
answer and it um it's really helped me
and hopefully our audience clarify
exactly what I mean by an existential
imperative which is that the free energy
principle doesn't tell you what you're
here for no it tells you if you're here
what are you doing like given your
phenotype um and given your culture and
etc etc so that's a really useful um
sort of explanation of exactly what I
was going for there um and actually it
points to something I said to Carl right
at the end of our podcast which at time
of recording this came out yesterday so
people should definitely check it out
because he for sure for sure he's on top
form which is I asked him I I mentioned
Thomas Nagel so Thomas Nel has this kind
of very romantic philosophical notion
that life is death is bad because life
is fundamentally good and it points to
kind of your fault experiment if we had
two worlds one with life and one without
life I think we would all intuitive
intuitively say the one with life is
better whether that has any metaphysical
import as you say is is up for grabs I
was going to I'm going to ask sort of um
jumping on the back of the initial thing
you said which was about connectedness
um and belongingness so if we take this
from a theoretical or computational
stance in active inference what this
looks like to me is we embody a model of
the world which um we can so we can make
fundamentally sound predictions about
how the world will unfold and how about
we will and how we will act to make that
world more um compatible with our
preferences now when that was for ized
initially in the active inference
literature immediately a response to
this came in the form of What's called
the dark room problem so this is saw
papers in 2011 2012 and and they've been
rebutted in multiple ways but the basic
idea is why don't humans just seek out
dark rooms where maybe they have access
to food and water but they don't really
see how but in a state where they don't
go and explore and they're not curious
because what you're seeing there is
actually a perfect coupling between your
predictions of the world and the world
and the way the world is unfolding to
your eyes so I was wondering whether you
had pondered the dark room problem and
where you see
exploration and epistemic affordances
coming into play here yeah I think that
the dark room problem I'm not I I I I'm
happy with all the other rebuttals um
and I don't and I don't know I don't
know I don't know them all so I may be
stepping on somebody else's toes so if I
am whoever you are I
yeah um I think this is you know a
lockin individualist model of cognition
and how we work and I think it is
therefore the presupposition well is
that no um that's actually I don't agree
with that presupposition that our
cognition is fundamentally
individualistic in that way I think we
are you know we are social sociocultural
mammals and let me point to one thing
you know yes measures of G are very
robustly predictive but you know it's
also really pred a very powerful way to
predicting your behavior your attachment
style this is also very robust now that
means think about what that actually
means and this you know and this goes
into the heart of religious Traditions
like agapic love right when you have a
child you have to invert your relevance
Arrow it's not how that being is
relevant to you you in invert everything
around this is agic love and how it's
different from erotic love or FIA love
you you invert everything around right
and so that it's how am I relevant to
this being how am I relevant to this
being and how can I be relevant in a way
that turns it into a person turns it
into an intelligent rational
self-reflective relevance realizer
predictive processor meaning maker right
and so well first of all where are my
attachment relationships in the dark
room well there's other people in the
dark room soon as there's other people
in the dark room all the problems that
you thought you got away from by putting
me in a dark room return other people
have different goals than me they have
different needs they're going to move
around differently right we're going to
have to decide about when and where and
how we gain access blah blah blah blah
blah all of that immediately unfolds
secondly and this is part of for E cogon
I think the evidence for extended
cognition distributed cognition that we
evolv to work in groups and the
collective intelligence of that is
actually our superpower and other people
are making this argument um I think
that's clear you standard thing take the
Wast and selection task put it an
individual person Highly Educated highly
intelligent second year you know
psychology and a top tier University
from the 1960s on you put him in the
Wast and selection task and only 10% get
it right right you replace that same
task with four people who are owed to
talk to each other and the success rate
goes from 10% to 82% reliably why
because we do opponent processing
between each other right you have biases
different from mine and if we work in
opponent processing not adversarial but
if I say you're probably a good source
for correcting my bias and I'm probably
a good source for correcting yours we
get the best dynamical
self-correction possible and so when you
add in the fact of the reality and
there's actually evidence empirical and
formal for the power of collective
intelligence the reality of attachment
well then the dark room right becomes
filled with other people who are trying
to you know band together to solve
problems that they can't solve
individually and then to me everything
that the dark room thought it had as an
absurd like a reductio absurdum
disappears that would be my response
yeah I think eventually the dark room
just becomes the world once you start
adding the things you need eventually
you know eventually it becomes a
civilization yeah I love I love all this
stuff on distributive cognition I spent
the first um six months of this year
working at UCL on um experiment finding
experimental ground for what's called
social Baseline Theory social Baseline
theory is this idea that humans like to
study a human being in a lab by itself
is to study a human being at deficit a
human being actually want it's
physiological arousal to take one um one
factor is at its Baseline when it's with
other people and it will FL uate
according to stuff like attachment style
or the relationship that one has with
that person which is really beautiful
but inverts our kind of well maybe not
common sense but our in
institutionalized notion of what it is
to be a person which is kind of alone
yeah wonderful well I'm going to take
this argument a little bit further if if
you let me um because this is something
that we spoke about a couple of months
ago and I think Mark might have a
different opinion so it' be cool to sort
of unpickle I have this um slightly
fuzzy wishy-washy idea that the notion
that okay so I always think about a
climber climbing a um rock face or a
climbing wall and the climbing wall is a
kind of beautiful canonical example of
an affordance-based landscape it's Rich
for the affordances it's got the toe
holes the finger holes so in many ways
what the um rock in terms of active
inference what it allows the rock
climber to do is to self-evidence um or
or find evidence for its own model about
itself um a success F rock climber yeah
now that's relatively well established
in the literature what isn't established
is my kind of again slightly wishy-washy
idea which is that the rock climber is
offering affordances to the wall and so
this this is why I about you know right
at the beginning of our conversation I
spoke about Mutual coupling so what
dynamical systems theory gives us what
um autop paresis gives us what act of
inference gives us is this idea that um
to exist is not to be this kind of
rified itself that um takes a objective
stance on the world and actually what it
is is this really the fundamental unit
of analysis should be this Dynamic
Mutual coupling between agent and Arena
to use your terminology yeah do you
think it's an over I mean I've spoken to
Mark about this and he he uses he said
it's something like an overextension of
the term affordances to say that the
human being is offering affordances to
the climbing wall I know Mark isn't here
to defend himself so again I'm not going
to put what but and I will definitely
raise this with him again but just for
your own ears how does that argument
sound to you I like the argument and
yeah I don't want to speak you little
Mark I'll only speak to the propositions
that you spoke on his behalf and I'm
very happy to I I mean Mark and I work
close together Mark is one of the best
people I know Mark's a former student of
mine I'm very proud of Mark so um uh but
um I actually agree with you now that
goes to another connection I make in my
work that would probably be a little bit
Str stranger to the ears of many of your
listeners they might say oh I get the
why he wants to connect uh you know
processing to relevance realization and
for coxy but now what you're doing and
this is where I do a lot of my what I
call my deeper ontological work and this
is where the hiigaran stuff really comes
to Bear is this is all the work I do on
on neoplatonism which may sound like
something very Arcane but it again um
here's here's the proposal that once we
really profoundly accept
affordances and once we accept that they
are reciprocally realizing I agree with
you the forance not only discloses
things about me it discloses things
about the world and that's a way in
which things like heer's notion of Truth
is ala as the as an event as the
disclosure rather than a static property
of our propositions um I think that hang
on now as filler argues and I've been
arguing for a while and John rusen uh
filler's book is called uh Neil play ISM
pager in the history of being relation
is ontological ground that relationality
is actually the the ultimate nature of
reality um heiger is actually turning
back towards this because what does that
give you you've had if you have that and
I think this is a fair way to put it if
you have that althetic notion of
affordance then you are getting back to
the neoplatonic theory of knowing by
Conformity knowing by participation and
the deeper argument goes something like
this um that if the fundamental grammar
of your cognition I don't mean the
content your content can go all wrong
and all but the fundamental grammar the
bottom up top down all all this stuff
we're talking about if it's not picking
up on something fundamental about how
reality is structured right then you
face a kind of profound solipsism a
profound kind of
skepticism um and I think that is
ultimately leads you into all kinds of
performative contradictions that I and I
agree with Whitehead they're as
devastating as propositional
contradiction there's a longer argument
there and I could point to please check
out some of my talks on on YouTube about
this longer argument like pix Stock's uh
aspects of Truth where she said you know
all the things we used to deize this
right we had the analytic synthetic
distinction that is broken down under
philosophical criticism uh we had the
theory fact distinction that is broken
down we we had the the like the is a
that has broken down like think about
relevance in is or an not well blah
right it's sort of both right right and
so her point is all the things that were
used to cleave and then what we tried to
do is we tried to make the logical world
the thing that sort of stuck the Two
Worlds together and that collapsed under
goal and other people and so we're back
to the idea that we either we either we
either go into the lock in cabinet in
which we're locked inside of our heads
we're somehow getting postcards sent to
us we think they might be from an
outside world that we think might be out
there and we're trying to build it from
the postcards and we're doomed that's
never going to get us there and so I
think if you have an althetic notion of
affordance you start to make the
argument that how reality is
realizing and how we are doing relevance
realization are fundamentally
participating in the same principles in
a profound way um and and I think yeah
that I I I I I have no doubt that Mark
might not not uh want to do this I think
Mark would be I would agree with Mark
that this is not a direct derivation
from sort of classic Frisian
presentations of active inference and
predicted processing daasi and brain we
should settle on a name uh but uh um but
I think if you make the connections
through deeper into Gibson deeper into
fory kogai deeper into heiger you get
back to this notion that with the
prevalent notion of knowing that when we
know something what we're doing is our
structural functional organization is
identifying with the structural
functional organization of the thing and
we are we are both participating in that
same form that same principle that same
grammar and that has all kinds of
metaphysical and ontological
consequences even uh ethical
consequences it means talking about the
true the good and the Beautiful becomes
something very relevant together yeah
yeah no this is this is exactly where I
wanted to go and exactly aligns with
with the way I'm thinking about the free
energy principle at the moment which is
I have a skepticism between the internal
and the external distinction yes this is
something I spoke about with so a
classic problem when one starts reading
active inference as I spoke about with
Carl is whether one would consider the
um the agent or the um internal Dynamics
is having having a model of the external
world or instantiating a model of the
external World model excellent excellent
this comes back to sort of cyber
cybernetic uh formulations what it is to
be a good regulator so col Ashby and all
of that stuff from the 50s and 60s so I
have an inherent skepticism because I
would I kind of take the stance actually
all that the internal Dynamics are doing
is instantiating a particularized form
of the external Dynamics and this is
very easy once you take out the picture
of a homuncular ego just if you look at
it in terms of just the particle physics
we're just a instantiation of some um of
the the physics that defines everything
else but we just we just actually seem
to have a kind of complexified Mark of
blanket or Mark of blanket form of that
but there's nothing particularly
distinct about that and we'll come to
Consciousness because maybe there is um
and that's I guess is the big elephant
in the room here but it's funny that you
mention haiger because haiger to my to
my
eyes um in my opinion and then obviously
draus and Merlo Ponte and the
phenomenologists followed haiger really
um he's the one who strikes at this um
established distinction between a
subject and an object yes so the
cartisian distinction and and then this
is where his kind of gripes with SRA
came in
now my question is is that yes if you
read haiger darine the ground of darine
is this kind of inter relationality Alf
is the disclosure of Truth in an inter
interrelational relationship so to speak
but there still seems to be some kind of
subject who um you know the the hammerer
who is hammering away at the nail now
from the perspective of the hammerer
he's not some rified ego who is
objectifying the nail that all that is
really being witnessed there from the
level of Consciousness is the dis
closure of
activity but still we can give a
description of a hammerer and a nail so
to what degree in your thinking do you
completely eradicate the subject object
distinction um and is there anything
that you think predictive processing has
to say about that I think uh well oh the
second question was don't worry worry
about second
question I'm happy to think about it
with you uh I have put a lot of thought
into the first question yeah um and so I
mean I think filler is right in his book
that our subjective objective divide is
our version of the appearance reality
distinction and and it's just our
version in the ancient world they had a
different version so ours is an in-out
metaphor how is the inner and the outer
connected um and the ancient world is
the problem of the one and the midi how
is the lower and the upper connected and
and it and and what what and once you
see that you realize that there's a
deeper structural problem that isn't
bound to the inner outer or the uh the
emergence and the emanation it's it's
this it's the connectivity issue and
what what what filler argues and there's
a lot of other people uh convergent on
this is like if you try if you if you go
with an Arista tilian metaphysics that
what's most real are substances in the
aristan sense which are things that can
independently exist um then this becomes
a deep problem for you and that kind of
ontology I would argue and I can make
the argument drives you towards a
nominalistic um epistemology um and then
you get you know aam's version of it or
K's version of it where all of the
patterns and all the information are
just in the mind which means the mind is
radically other because it is the only
place that information intelligibility
actually exists and the world is
profoundly AB absurd in a deep deep way
way and I think that leads you into uh
well first of all it makes science
impossible and it leads you into all
kinds of existential and moral dilemmas
and if you then take a look at the logic
of trying to get you can't actually and
this is what filler does very carefully
you can't actually get relations out of
properties that belong to the relata the
relations have to preed the rata in a
very important way so I think there's a
deep at a very deep level I do want to
call it into question I do want to
challenge that uh that go first of all
we it's historical it's cultural we we
pretend as if that is the only way in
which human beings have related to the
world like I said even in the west
that's not their problem in the ancient
world their problem is the problem of
the one and the many it's not the
problem of the in order now what does
this all ground in I think this grounds
in the common problem of the
relationship between appearance and
reality and here's where I could now say
something that aligns with my previous
argument about
relationality see so and I'm going to
borrow a term from uh recour here the
hermeneutics of Suspicion the
hermeneutics of Suspicion is that appear
and we've got it because of Freud and
nii and blah blah blah there's
historical reasons and those are
valuable critiques by the way but the
Hermon of Suspicion says appearances are
distorting they're deceptive they're
distractive right they're disruptive and
what we should do is always question
whether or not they are leading us into
reality now maral Ponty has a great
argument against that that he gets from
I maybe he doesn't get but it's it's in
Plato which is wait you're treating real
like red like you can just say you can
look at an isolated thing and say that's
real but real is a comparative term so
of course is illusion to say this is an
illusion is to say this is an illusion
in comparison in relation to something
that is more real and that thing is in
relation so on and so forth right and
what that means is first of all you have
to see that those judgments are
inherently relational and secondly you
have to call into question the her the
the the
independence of the hermeneutics of
Suspicion the hermeneutics of Suspicion
is actually parasitic on the
hermeneutics of beauty there right
depends on there being things that we
agree on by saying that's where
appearance
discloses reality rather than distorting
it right and then as soon as you do that
that undercuts the Deep divide because
you ultimately make these divisions
between the one and the many or the
subject and the object by getting a
harmonics of Suspicion into the
appearance reality distinction that's at
least the argument I would make
interesting yeah I I like the I like the
suspicion of buying
Ness uh inherent in all of this um it it
speaks to me and I think it speaks to
people who interested in active
inference and the notion of sort of
philosophical vagueness as well um at
what point is something real is is
fundamentally a comparative term in the
web of things that could be considered
real um yeah that that that's right yeah
I I I I'm trying to do this without
invoking a binary but um you mentioned
earlier 4E cognitive scientists do have
their critiques of active inference um
and and predictive processing and I I
will stick with active inference
actually for now and I will explain why
later um it's not that interesting so
this this was people like Tony KERO or
Ed bags um who who are radical in
activists and what they're critiquing in
a sense is an internalist picture of yes
Act of inference so this is some again
I'm not putting words into people's
mouths but if you read um yob how's um
2016 paper about self-
evidencing some of the language May to
some people imply that there is a
homunculus that has a representation or
picture of the world and this to the
ears of a inactivist is deeply
worrying I would love to as a four
cognitive scientist um with obviously
vested interest in predicted processing
as well I'd love to just hear your take
on that debate and um again without
striking at binaries and whether you
think those critiques are
legitimate well I mean depends what you
mean by legitimate I mean you know
there's also the ones that Evan Thompson
made and I hold Evan in very high regard
um I mean they're legitimate in that
they are they they're wellmade arguments
in peer-reviewed journals and so we we
have no right to be dismissive of them
well if I was to say if I was to say
that let's take as an axiom of active
inference like this is just um this
isn't the case but let's just say for
sake of argument that you have some um
internalist representations of a
statistical model right so you are in a
sense you're not just embodying a model
you actually have a model so again it
comes back to that distinction we're
talking about would a inactivist
critique of that internalism be um be
justified
um so the reason why I'm hesitating is
this is landing on the swamp of what do
we mean by
representation uh which is I mean
so does the thermostat represent the
temperature in the environment and where
and everything I'm going to say is
controversial because of the swamp so I
want that understood please right I
would say no because what's needed is
right there there might be some cor
there there might be co-variation but
that what I think the critiques of the
co-variation model of representation
locks ultimately model that what did so
we had the idea that representations
have to be similar to what they
represent that's how they represent and
then you have all the problems with
similarity and Aristotle even could
bring that down um and then lock replac
it with the covariation model to have a
representation is I have something in my
head that reliably co-varies with
something in the world and that's how it
represents it and then the problem with
the covariations is they don't give you
um the specificity for example of
thought right so this is covarying with
a bottle with a tool with a man-made
object like which is it those are not
the same things so not those are not the
same ideas but the this is coar and
causally with all of that and you have
you have the problem then of aspectual
isation and and the loan answer of
course is we get we get aspects by doing
representation but I agree with surl
that that's the wrong way around that
any representation is inherently
aspectual when I represent this as a
bottle I'm only picking up on some of
its properties in so far as they are
relevant to each other in so far as they
are relevant to me so representation
depends on as aspect realization which
depends on relevance realization and
this is not what you do with relevance
realization you do not represent all the
facts judge them to be irrelevant and
then zero in so it's ultimately
non-representational so what I would say
is I I don't know at some level there's
something like
representations and but if if I agree
with many arguments that representations
are more than co-variation but there's
this kind of carness and aspect caring
and aspectual isation through them then
they depend on relevance realization
which grounds in autopolis and is deeply
intertwined with predictive processing
that would be my argu that would be my
response Splendid and I guess I guess
what intuitively supports a more
representation this picture is
consciousness um I think Consciousness
is be going to become a recurring theme
in this podcast um well it's the Holy
Grail right it is it is the Holy Grail
um and so so I guess my question here is
is that if one was to adopt a radically
inactivist
view there's nothing in that picture
which um needs Consciousness so why
couldn't my Mutual coupling with the
world just happen with the lights off so
this is a argument I guess that's rooted
in Charmers um 1995 paper which is you
can give me the function but you can't
give me the why why are the lights on
and so I guess in in other words my my
question to is yes that we may have
relevance realization um
preceding perception or pered or or or
grounding
perception yeah then why do we have
perception in the first
place so um again I'm gonna give a gist
of an argument that I've spoken about at
length elsewhere and I'm trying to get
published on and presented at
conferences and so forth so um
I don't think you can separate the
function and the nature questions which
is what trauma's hard problem uh relies
on is it yeah yeah you've given me the
function but you've tell me nothing
about the nature I don't think function
works ontologically like that I think
function has to be plugged into the
ontology and I think as soon as we're
talking about the ontology of anything
within a living organism we're talking
about something functional so I think
the questions have to be answered
interconnected so let's go let's go back
let's say that you give
me that um any cognitive agent has to be
do doing anticipatory relevance
realization or it's not going to be a
general Problem Solver and then when
it's doing that it has to be aspectual
ising its world
right right it's it's not Rea it's not
doing all of the all of this but this as
a bottle or the molecule as food the
molecule right and then if you then
start to pay attention
to let's look at the Continuum of
Consciousness uh let's look at the
possibility which I have experienced
that's not even the right sentence many
people have and this is Foreman's idea
of something like the pure Consciousness
event and the pure Consciousness event
doesn't
have well actually I need a distinction
here I'm going to claim it doesn't have
one type of qualia but it has another
type of qualia in it it doesn't have
adjectival qualia there's no red there's
no blue there's no cap there's no dark
there right you're not even conscious of
Consciousness you're just conscious yeah
right but what what it still has is it
still has the adverbial qualia it still
has a sense of
heess now and the heess is profound
presence that's the language that you
The nness
Eternity the the the integration right
the togetherness it's everything is one
so all the adverbial qualia are still
there and you still have Consciousness
that shows that the adjectival qualia
are not necessary to Consciousness now I
have the other arguments to show they're
probably not sufficient because if I
give you sort of atomic blips of bless
and greenness and they're not bound
together and there's not a heess and a
nness so you can any way Orient on them
I don't think you have Consciousness
either right um so I'm not saying that
adav Quia don't exist I'm saying that
we've held Consciousness Hostage to them
yeah and what I'm proposing to you is
that what Consciousness is doing is
these adverbial qualia which are just
right
salients which is just relevance
realization which is as far as we can
tell tied to the best evidence we have
it's all controversial about the
function of Consciousness it's tied up
with working memory and attention which
are both doing higher order relance
realization we need to seem to need
Consciousness for situations of
complexity novelty or IL definedness
ones that are really demanding on
relevance realization so you can make a
pretty and there's a lot of convergence
actually on what the function of
Consciousness is relevance realization
and I think if you plug in relevance
realization you can at least get all the
adverbial qualia and that I think gives
you a lot of what Consciousness actually
is cool um yeah let's stay on that
verbial qualia because I I'd like to
integrate what you've just said with a
more active inference account of
Consciousness which there are and and
they're they're also diverse but one
well I have to ask a question before is
does
Foreman um say that miness so um feeling
that this experience is mine does he is
is that one of his verbal qualia that
persists in the pure Consciousness event
so that that's another Thicket because
the debate about this is a raging debate
Evan Thompson actually has a good
Anthology on this on the self no self
debate right right
and I think
it's I think it's
reasonable and complies with most of the
evidence which of course is self-report
after the fact which is problematic blah
blah blah blah I agree with all of that
I'm not dismissing that but that's what
we basically have to go on right now um
that the ego narrative sense of mine and
me and I goes away I whether or not that
is a complete loss
of the self
as as where relevance realization is
happening or something like that yeah um
that that I'm not I'm not convinced that
that second thing is the case okay I
think so if you would allow me and this
is tortured distinction a distinction
between the ego and the self I think
these experiences very much the ego goes
away I'm very suspicious of the claim
that the self goes away because people
are readily able to recall these
experiences this is what Forman does
report and I would report to you and
seamlessly integrate them into their
autonoetic autobiographical memory there
isn't any weird dis jarring or where was
I during yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah okay
excellent the reason why I asked that is
because um a lot of self modeling in
active inferences based on the work of
Thomas matzinger so Thomas matzinger is
such a wonderful addition to this
conversation so had a wonderful
conversation with him not that long ago
really love on my Chanel amazing I think
he's I think he's such an underrated and
important philosopher totally agree yeah
yeah so he's got this notion of so he
makes a distinction between phenomenal
self modeling and an ontological self so
people intuitively even everyone
listening to this podcast even the way
we act on a day-to-day basis is in Li of
an ontological self so we can't help but
really think of ourselves as being this
Soul this Cari and soul but anyway
Metson invokes this notion of phenomenal
self modeling how the system appears to
itself and he's got this um minimal
phenomenal self which which has been
unpicked in other ways but he normally
he speaks generally of presentness
mindness and perspec ibless exactly what
I've been talking about yeah exactly
this gets fleshed out in some of the act
of inference work people like jaob ho um
Carl and yob lonowski have used um
metsing good work for several papers and
then on the other end of that we have
what Carl turned an epistemic agent
model which is the self that s um the
system that sees itself as epistemic in
the sense that it can retrieve past
memories to inform future decisions and
agentive in the fact that it can conduct
allostatic action I.E um action to
retain some homeostatic equilibrium
given what it knows about the future so
me putting on a jumper before I go
outside because I know it's going to be
colder outside than it is inside the
reason why I invoke the minimal
phenomenal selfhood is because and Carl
actually outlines this in the podcast we
did together that Consciousness may be
Downstream in a sense on one a deep
temporal model and from that the sense
of agency and he has an argument from um
referring to Dimensions um not in terms
of sort of millimeter size but in terms
of um the degree to which you have
embedded Markov
blankets um that when we're distant from
our actuators what we end up doing is we
have to have a way of distinguishing
what's my action from what's your action
or from what the world how the world has
acted on us and in doing that we come up
with a self other distinction but also
the notion of an agentive self the idea
that I can change the world in
accordance to
preferences as as I mentioned beforehand
so to sort of paraphrase Carl what that
seems to be suggesting is that
Consciousness is actually rooted in
selfhood and I know there's this whole
argument in metzinger about whether
that's the
case that's why I ask whether mindness
is also part of these pure Consciousness
events or whether it's kind of a post
talk inference just wondering whether
you had any ideas about that notion um
and whether we can truly have have
Consciousness without at least a sense
of
self right okay so
um uh let me try a few things first of
all um I don't think it's inevitable
that human beings model themselves as
Souls I think that's a western postc
cartisian uh way of and that's even and
and then the Soul as a
uh monatic single substance can put it
that way uh you don't that's not even
the case in uh the ancient world of the
West certainly not the case in other
parts of the world Etc so I I I I
hesitate that that's um the claim that's
part of how the Machinery must unfold
sure and then secondly um I I worry
about saying you know that that that
because it isn't a soul there isn't a
self this is a weird notion of again of
a substance ontology being just
presupposed in an unquestioned manner I
mean look we've discovered most things
aren't substances this table which would
be a classic arisan substance is not a
substance it's it's a dynamical system
of atoms and quarks and blah and we
don't go oh well because tables aren't
substances they aren't real like that we
don't do that so I like I I I I I I just
I I want to just note that I'm worried
that there's a substance sure ontology
creeping in here and leading to certain
conclusions now that idea about uh uh
this there's I can't remember the name
of the people uh and I apologize for
that there is a fairly recent Theory Of
Consciousness that trying to respond to
all the liit experiments and things like
that um arguing that well conscious ious
is sort of after the fact but
Consciousness is actually for the future
yeah conscious so the idea here is
consciousness is emerges out of the
evolution of episodic memory so the
function of Consciousness is to allow us
to create an episodic memory of
something we have already done uh right
and the point about the episodic memory
is soon as you get into episodic memory
you get into perspectival knowing that's
what an episode is right you have a
perspective right on a situation what
you found Salient and relevant how your
actions and right and the arena coupled
or didn't couple the affect that all all
of that all of that that's so bound up
with Consciousness and and then the and
the point that they make and I totally
agree with this is soon as you agree
that there are multiple kinds of knowing
not just propositional and procedural
but also perspectival and participatory
you get the argument that episodic
memory affords perspectival knowing
which allows you to solve problems that
you can't solve without perspectival
knowing you can pick up on the world the
world discloses itself in ways that it
is not otherwise disclosable to you and
then Consciousness emerges as an
optimization on the formation of
episodic memory so it is optimally
transfer appropriate for the future
right and then you get it is a sense of
agency but it's not a billiard ball
agency yeah it's the it's this kind of
longitudinal agency and to tell you the
truth given the humi and critiques
that's actually the kind of agency the
self has it has this kind of
longitudinal uh right agency around
episodes it doesn't have this I'm an
some sort of uncaused cause and moved
mover Within Myself which I think is
both a ridiculous proposal ontologically
and an and an ethically undesir why
would I want such a thing right like
it's completely arbitrary I I think my
life is being lived I'm trying to change
myself so that I am my thoughts as
determined by what is true my action as
determined by what is good and my uh
perception is determined by by what is
beautiful as I possibly can I would like
to lose all my freedom in that sense um
um and so I think if we move to to the
right level of analysis and Gallagher
makes a convergent argument about this
that when we're talking about agency and
selfhood we're not talking at that liit
scale we're not talking at where's the
first movement of the billiard ball
chain we're talking more about no no no
how are we building this longterm
virtual engine that enhances our
predictive agency in the world yeah
absolutely and that and Gallagher's work
is very convergent with Thomas matzinger
of course uh and so this just for our
audience this these arguments and this
notion of the narrativized self is well
fleshed out in active inference
literature um so I could point you yeah
I would probably start with the the fris
and lonowski papers there are two
wonderful papers about self-construction
under Act of inference and and then I
have a convergent argument coming out of
Daniel Daniel hudo who is also in the 4E
right the narrative practice hypothesis
and he argues that any mindsight ability
any ability to see in other people's
into other people's mental States you
know attributing beliefs and desires to
them uh
requires well for example if I'm going
to attribute a belief and desire I need
to know something about your character
yeah are you lying or not right I need
to know something about the context the
setting like what's going on in this
situation are you tired is that a small
child so you're not really lying when
you tell them at Christmas time that
there's a Santa Claus right uh right and
I need to know what the is what the
problem notice what I'm talking about
here I need to know all the elements of
narrative Daniel Judo points out we
practice narrative incessantly and
unlike many of the other things
including language which we scaffold for
children we scaffold narrative for our
our kids I had to sit through the
Teletubbies twice in which you have to
sit through these really impoverished
narratives because we're scaffolding
this up because narrative ability gives
us the right gives us the set of skills
the sets of states of mind with the
perspectives taking therein and the
traits of character that allow us to
pick up on other people's mental States
and I think that is also a function of
the S the function of selves is to make
us agentically predictive to each other
right exactly exactly and there's
another there's another convergent
argument in Act of inference which is
that um only in the context of other
people like you would you ever come to
the inference that there is something
that is like to be
you yeah yeah if you were cones with
vski that converges with the whole vatan
approach to the development of
metacognition and self-awareness which I
think is right right right right and of
course um your colleague at um just
pointing people in different directions
your colleague at Toronto or former
colleague Jord Peterson um yeah has a
whole uh literature on literature and
narrative and he has a conversation with
car on his podcast which is um deeply
intriguing about these kind of
alignments of the free energy principle
and and narrative John I wanted to also
speak about flow
States
um you've written about flow as yes the
sort of locus of implicit learning um as
you know I've just been writing up a
paper on Flow um from an active
inference perspective so I'd love to be
able to sort of see maybe where we align
where we don't align and try and sort of
unpick that just as a for warning my
paper the paper that I've written with
my wonderful co-authors is not out yet
but it should be coming out soon um
so I want to I have not yet read your
paper because you you suggested waiting
uh yes the paper paper's gone through um
modifications as papers are want to
do it's in the final stages so you have
access to it so so please feel free to
read it I will read it then I will read
it going for I can give I can give a
very brief overview so to not
disadvantage you um my the basic thesis
of the basic perspective that we take on
the paper is about self- modeling under
flow States so that's the main thing
that we're looking at and the
attenuation of an epistemic agent model
because what we're arguing is that
certain Precision weighting mechanisms
are lending it
are leading the organism to undertake
pragmatic action seeking out pragmatic
affordances um rather than engage in
what car or other offers would call
epistemic
foraging now I think where we might have
a point of difference here is that I
have a section on Flow States and
learning and I think this is a really
interesting point because your paper
speaks about implicit learning whereas
I'm and and this and to to make it
transparent this is there are I've heard
different perspectives on this but my
current opinion is that in flow States
what you're getting is a reinforcement
of the skills that you actually um
picked up through epistemic work so I
have the example of a violinist the
violinist must undergo a certain period
of exploration of epistemic foraging
which comes with this kind of selft talk
this real prominence of myself as a
knowing thing yeah right and then what
it does is over time through learning
you get high Precision um over the
beliefs about that action in terms of
the technical detail and then that Bec
becomes kind of the foundation on which
you can then go and do more epistemic
work and then that become and then that
expertise development is stepwise in a
sense I mean you can picture it either
way but critically and where we differ
is that I'm arguing that actually in the
moment of flow itself you're just
garnering more evidence for the
capacities and the policies that you
already
have so I'd like to start there and see
and see what you think of that
claim um
so we as you point out Leo Ferraro AR
and her and I we argue um something
different um which is why you're
bringing it up uh we argue that um um
that learning is inevitably occurring
even in the flow situation and so
there's Improvement um and that's why if
the environment doesn't have the
capacity to renew uh it challenges on
you you will very quickly fall out of
the Flow State so the argument is well
why don't you just stay in the Flow
State well the argument is because
eventually you get a Mastery over the
environment um which means you still
start to exceed the demands and so
phenomenologically when I'm in the Flow
State like in sparring or lecturing um
I'm finding tremendous amount of insight
and Innovation uh coming out
um now this is where it might get tricky
um because is procedural Innovation a
restructuring especially uh is that a
restructuring of um uh your information
and therefore have new capacities in it
new emergent abilities or is it just a
reinforcement and I don't this we might
get into thesis's ship here which is
going be problematic uh
but the one of the defining
phenomenological features of the Flow
State and I'm uh I want to be clear I'm
not pinning you down on this but I do
think it's relevant evidence is the
ongoing sense of Discovery there's a
sense of Discovery there there's a sense
of coming to know things you did not
know before and of course when the flow
state is in much more comprehensive
expertise not like they playing tennis
or maybe like just your optimal gripping
on the world people come to think they
have learned something deeply profound
uh about reality so I tend to think that
there's evidence for transformative
learning happening up and Beyond just
reinforcement Lear okay yeah I I I like
the return to the phenomena um you know
draas has this phrase which I will
definitely use over and over again in
this podcast which is when in doubt
return to the phenomena um the way that
we have cast it is that there's this
idea in the literature about a hyper
prior that the world is changing so that
we have a prior that the world is
changing and that is adaptive for us
because we don't get stuck in the same
free energy Minima now if that prior is
always at play what ends up happening
Downstream on that is that my inference
about my own abilities deteriorates over
time and we and we we experience that I
guess I mean like if I play tennis today
and then I play tennis in a week's time
I'm probably going to have less Fidelity
in my own capacities in the week's time
than I do if I play tomorrow having
follow today yeah yeah and so our
argument is that the positive effect
that's part of the flow state is
Downstream on the rise that's generated
when you actually violate that hyper
prior that the world is changing because
what you're getting evidence for is that
your policy still work in the world that
you would have beener you would have
thought didn't lend itself to your
policies working and there's this idea
um Casper hp's paper and his co-authors
in 2021 that affecting active inference
is about um basically your model doing
better than you thought it would do um
and and this actually comes a lot into
what Mark talks about in terms of
aerodynamics so so I'm
wondering yeah I don't
know yourself well see I I think that's
right I think and and and the problem of
course is you can get an infinite
regress so well I'll say well the mod
the the things here and you'll say well
there needs to be something a h a hyper
prior behind that and then we can that's
what I mean about thesis's ship yeah
yeah yeah so again I would say well what
what are you getting better at and what
you're getting better at I would argue
is
um not St like so expertise is generally
built around like uh giving you a well
like a specific domain we can talk about
um the possibility of sort of meta
expertise if we want but what I mean by
that is once you've got expertise you've
gotten really good at within a certain
domain at formulating the problems
you're fronting as for you well- defined
problems uh that's one way in which an
expert is sort of reliably different
from a novice a novice goes in this is
an IL defined problem the expert goes
goes in and say no it's this problem and
this is the right what you need to do
this and this and this and this and this
okay so we agree with that but I think
what's happening right and and maybe
this is the gray area between your
position in mind I think what's
happening is we're discovering new ways
in which we can turn well-defined
problem sorry ill-defined States into
well-defined problems we're going
something like I didn't realize I could
adapt to that situation but I can yeah
and and that sounds similar uh but for
me that's that's an Insight experience
uh and that's what like it's an Insight
flow because you're you're you're
getting an extension of your cognitive
capacity because you have restructured
what you take to be the like your abil
your your problem formulation of the
world that's
that's yeah I mean to supplement that I
I actually I I don't disagree um on that
not but the way I would formulate that
and this actually isn't in the paper
it's in the paper in some sense but it's
not a fully fleshed out argument because
it wasn't hyper relevant I'm glad
there's another really quality paper on
Flow coming there not there's really
there's really nothing um when we
published the paper we were literally
the only paper talking about the
cognitive processes that work in flow I
I yeah it's it's a it's a bizarre one um
there's very little on skillful coping
generally within yeah Cog science but as
I said I think that's why I said there
should be more
phenomenology active or cognitive
science convergence what what we kind of
mentioned in brief Is That Flow if we
take the sort of macro perspective on
what flow is it can also be this kind of
humming between the pragmatic and the
epistemic boundary yeah so maybe when
you're realizing oh I can reframe this
um kind of uh perplexing problem as
actually something manageable what
you're doing there is Maybe just
slightly exiting the flow doing some
epistemic foraging returning because
something I want to make really clear to
everyone listening as
well the when we talk about epistemic
action and pragmatic action in terms of
expected free energy or active inference
it's not like the agent goes I'm doing
pragmatic action right now
anding right it's all part of the actual
maths right so if you looked at the
maths it's like firstly you can do a bit
of both right at the same time like that
that's a thing but it's also like the
action policies that we're talking about
here John and I these are not protracted
seven hours of just like pragmatic
action no no these have to be very
temporally thin because the world is
volatile right the world is constantly
changing and so you have to be able to
not just pin all your hopes or put all
your eggs in one basket in terms of an
action
policy and so actually fundamentally our
Divergence might well be a semantic
thing which is that I'm talking very
much about the synchronic nature of
being in flow right now and like I have
for for Simplicity I have that boundary
between pragmatic and epistemic whereas
if you take a kind of more macro
perspective as that flow State as the
concerto unfolds you could be humming at
that boundary and doing learning as well
yeah I I I really look forward to your
paper because I think that sounds like
actually a powerful way in which the
theories could be integrated uh together
um I'm also interested in a question
that's emerging out of this dis well I
I've already been interested in the
question but it emerges out of what
we're talking about because I'm
interested because I I think there's
there might be an additional thing
um because there's you can flow in a in
a situation and it doesn't transfer it
doesn't transfer to other domains video
game addiction is the classic Model you
can flow in the game you can't flow in
the world so you get depressed in the
world you can flow in the game and so
you want to stay in the game more and
more and more um that for that's very
different than how I flow in ta chian ta
chian in fact other people pointed this
out in me the the the flow states that I
cultivate in taii Chan I can they are
cultivated in such a way that they
transfer broadly and deeply to many
other domains and I'm interested in the
this this this this sort of ritual
framework because what what you get is
this ritual and this philosophical
framework dosm and other e other
practices and ecologia practices around
so that it broadens um like it transfers
in powerful ways and and I'm wondering
um what the differences are and also if
how does that show up is there a
phenomenological difference there I mean
so now really really really weakly
anecdotally right uh in terms of
phenomenological practice I do get a
sense of a difference when between when
I'm just flowing and when I'm flowing in
a ritual context so if I enter into a
violin Hall and like let's say an expert
in playing the violin and I see a crowd
and I see my violin and I see the whole
stage what I end up getting is this um
so habits are quite well codified within
Act of inference you get this kind of
contextual cue that like in layman's T
although this is we're saying this isn't
happening propositionally it's time for
me to play the violin and this can look
like Precision over beliefs about your
own action so what this is again not
something I've thought about necessarily
with any depth because is just something
that youve brought up I'm wondering
whether that contextual cue what you're
happening when you're doing taichi and
then maybe what you're doing when you're
lecturing is that your your your system
is seeing similarities in that in the
contexts and doing similar Precision
waiting in other in in a separate do in
a separate domain yeah I think that's
right and I think what philosophical
Frameworks do is they reverse engineer
that they try to uh find out what might
be similar or maybe even invariant
across many contexts and then build that
back into the specific context in which
you are doing the practice to exactly
afford that transfer appropriate
processing I think that's right I think
there's something else also going on
with the queuing and this goes into
apter's meta motivational theory we can
be e we can be broadly speaking we frame
our arousal in two different ways when
we're in a telic mode and we're working
towards some where where where the
reward is found in the external goal
then increased effort is experienced as
frustration and and then it and then it
increases too much I get anxiety but I
mean if I'm doing something where the
goal is the behavior itself like making
love or doing poetry then the increased
not infinitely obviously but the
increased arousal is framed as positive
as excitement right right right right uh
and so I think also and so after talks
about safety uh safety frame
right let's call the first atelic Mode
work and the um the paratelic mode um um
play and I think ritual has to do with
serious play and I've got a whole
argument about that but I think also
what what you're doing in the context is
you're you're trying to cue people into
the play mode uh because the play mode
allows them to model themselves their
arousal as positive rather than as
negative and that allows them and I
think there's a deep connection between
this paratelic Framing and chick sahi's
I think accurate claim that flow is
autotelic doing it for its own sake
right yeah yeah cool yeah I I like the
notion of effort here recognize that one
of the fundamental factors or
fundamental characteristics of flow is
uh perceived effortlessness yes even
though you can even though you can have
sort of very uh peripheral cues that you
might be expending a lot of metabolic
energy exactly right um and just for the
given this is the active inference
institutes podcast just for those
interested in the computational framing
of that within active inference Thomas
par has got a paper out this year on
cognitive effort and active inference so
that gives a kind of nice computational
modeling picture of that which actually
leads me to a much broader question
because I know we're we haven't got too
much more time which is I've noticed in
myself to be totally candid that I've
started like I I learned about flow and
sixcess M High through you and and
through other people but mainly as a
philosophical notion um and now I'm
viewing it as a computational notion yes
yeah do you worry about that do you
worry that if we rely too much on comput
not not just computational models but
maths physics we in some ways reduce the
phenomena in a way that's detrimental
not just because it's not romantic or
that it's but like that we're missing
something
fundamentally well it depends I mean
that's a really important question we
could do two hours on just that question
uh but if you think that a leveled
ontology is actually the way ontology is
um that the level at which we do science
is as ontologically real as the quantum
level we discover when we're doing
science and I think you have to come to
that conclusion right and I have
extended Arguments for that elsewhere
then uh there's then you can make a
clean philosophical distinction between
explaining a way in a reductive fashion
and explaining that actually enriches
your appreciation for the phenomena uh
now if the computational stuff the
computational stuff to my mind well
let's say what the argument we were just
exploring um has Merit then notice what
we're saying we're saying well what the
computational modeling actually does is
actually shows why this sometimes very
obscure philosophical framework is
really important yeah it's actually
doing some really important work and you
can't get rid of it you can't dispense
with it and and and and and and that
would mean that kind of some of the
stuff we're doing where we're trying to
commodify flow and take it out of those
those Frameworks you know and do the
thing we do and you know sell books and
right um it's actually Mis
misrepresenting the phenomena in a in a
in a way that we can philosophically and
scientifically critique and say wait
wait right this phenomena has the power
it has because chick sahai said it's an
evolutionary marker for adaptivity and
then well making it adoptive is how
broadly and deeply is it transferring
out of the situation and then the
philosophical framework really matters
to what it is and how it functions and
so if you if you can make a distinction
and you need an ontological distinction
to make this distinction but if you can
make a distinction between explaining
and explaining away then then I think
it's possible to say no no when I do
these things and and to be fair to me
darus I get a lot of people people who
you know are from various religious and
spiritual backgrounds and they come in
and they say thank you so much for your
work I now I much better
appreciate this right this experience or
that experience or the Flow State or
this mystical State because you didn't
try and tell me it's nothing but you
tried to say this is what it's doing and
this is why you like it and value it so
much but do you think your
work to kind of yeah to to look at that
personal vantage point do you think
you've managed to keep like cuz if I
without being sort of embarrassingly
lording people should watch Awakening
from the meaning crisis um not only for
the content but also just the way you
present it which is just so magical um
so thanks I mean it's it's really
inspired a lot of the way that I think
science should be done and philosophy
should be done what what is it about I
think you know anyone who watches that
recognizes there's something kind of
special going on there the ideas are
living through you you're they're
breathing through you you're breathing
through them there's this really
beautiful coupling again we'll come back
to that between you and the
ideas what what is it about that kind of
symphasis of the philosophy and the sort
of more hard cognitive science do you
think made that project so
successful I suppose it's a view of the
role of cognitive science what cognitive
science is doing
um I think what cognitive science does
is
it well I'll try and do it sort of
narratively uh uh and I do this in the
series I think you know the even the
notion of Mind we've been invoking mind
and cognition is equivocal uh because it
means one thing to the neuroscientists
who's studying the brain and looking at
uh neurons and anatomical networks and
perhaps functional networks it means a
different thing to the artificial
intelligence person who's building
algorithms and
puristic um and doing reinforcement
learning and blah blah means a different
thing to the psychologist who's studying
human behavior with experiments and
running stats and they talk about
working memory they don't talk so much
right and it means a different thing to
the linguist and a different thing to
the cultural Anthropologist by the way I
include them because they were the
people that have been studying
distributed cognition and collective
intelligence they mattered yeah um now
if you think about it on this analogy
it's like there are different countries
speaking different languages and here's
the thing that has great value
specialization has great value I'm not
dismissing that I am not dismissing that
but each one of these is talking about a
different level and here's what I think
I would State as a very plausible claim
I think it's unlikely that these levels
in reality the brain information
processing behavioral linguistic
sociocultural levels are independent
from each each other I think they causal
influence and constrain each other so we
are missing something important about
the Mind by right not getting clear
about the relationship between these
levels we can be equivocating and we are
we have a fragmented notion if we don't
capture the relations of constraint and
causation between these different levels
of cognition and mind and so I think the
proper function of cognitive science is
to use philosophy's skills
of creating bridging discourses creating
bridging conceptual right uh vocabulary
theoretical grammar so that these
different disciplines can talk to each
other in reciprocally reconstructive
ways as a way of converging on the
causal and constraint relationships
between the levels rather than trying to
compete or say the bottom level is the
only real real level so that for me they
all live together they are doing and I'm
sorry to invoke it again they're doing
opponent processing between each other U
and that's how that's that's what that's
that's what inhabits me when I'm doing
cognitive science that Vision I call it
synoptic integration yeah it's well it's
wonderful to see um so so I mean like I
think we I mean that's the cognitive
scientist that I'm aspiring to be um I
think you've called it a big picture
cognitive scientist as well yes and one
of the things one of I felt very only
for a while you know I I was doing
relevance realization which is a big
picture and then to my great Delight
another big picture for EOG side down
the and then to my even greater
happiness another big picture came down
the road which is you know the
predictive processing framework and I
think they are more convergent than op
uh adversarial and I well you've heard
me arguing about how we can integrate
them together excellent yeah yeah yeah I
would say maybe it's just bias
active inferences or prics processing is
a big picture cognitive scientist from
the physics and the maths all the way
what what we're trying to do to the
phenomena to what it is like to be a to
be a human being to have conversations
like this John it's um I it was you know
I can't say it was better than I
expected because I knew it was going to
be wonderful but um you're full of just
thrilling insights and speaking to you
listening to you is always such a
wonderful learning experience where that
happens in flow or without flow um but I
just wanted to thank you so very much
for I know you're extremely busy um but
for giving us your time where can people
find you what have you got coming up um
I'm sure people are curious so the most
immediate thing for this conversation um
is the talk I gave at Leiden on the
predictive processing Symposium it's up
on my channel I think it's the second
most recent video on my channel on
YouTube we can put it in the yeah where
I I I try to go into the nuts and bolts
of how you could integrate uh predictive
processing and relevance realization
Theory together so people might find
that and I've got a lot of good feedback
on that uh for being sort of clear clear
and and a good argument um so I would
recommend that when people are
interested in uh the the the the broader
implications of this um Awakening for
the meeting crisis and then after
Socrates also after Socrates is where I
take all of this in all of this stuff
and well how do you turn it into
practices in order to overcome
self-deception and enhance relevance
realization become more wise and
virtuous um and so they can take a look
there um the arguments around
neoplatonism um there are several videos
around that how I've tried to connect
neoplatonism to for eoai and relevance
realization of predictive processing as
as we saw in this podcast but in the
neoplatonism I'm working on my third big
series um walking the philosophical Silk
Road which will be on Zen neoplatonism
trying to see if we could bring an
integration an opponent processing not
an adversarial one an opponent
processing between Zen and neoplatonism
to give us a rich philosophical
framework by which like the
philosophical road we could trade ideas
and move between worlds without um
having to descend into well tribalism
and other such things wonderful
wonderful well again it was absolutely
my pleasure I apologize I've got a
slight cold so if I've been a little
sniffly or nasle oh no we blame on we
can blame it on the London weather but
um I'd love to have you back on at some
point um your your work is is truly
inspiring so thank you so much John for
me and The Institute thank you darus I'm
happy to come back on and you know if it
if it turns out that you know Mark and I
come on together that would be thrilling
as well great we will definitely get
that sorted all right thank you thank
you